"Vitamin E Supplements for Cancer,
immunity, and Longevity"
Randomized controlled trials
show that daily
vitamin D supplementation
appears to reduce the risk
of acute respiratory infections
in children and adolescents,
but it does not seem
to make a difference in adults,
nor does D appear effective
for boosting
antibody responses
to influenza vaccination.
What about vitamin E?
Most places, you'll read
that there are eight different
tocopherols and tocotrienols
that are collectively known
as vitamin E,
but only alpha-tocopherol
has been shown
to protect against
human vitamin E deficiency.
So alpha-tocopherol
is the only bona fide vitamin E
and is the one found
in vitamin E supplements.
There are observational data
suggesting
those self-reporting
supplementation with vitamin E
have, for example,
better pneumonia outcomes,
but only interventional trials
can prove if this is the case.
Compared to placebo supplements,
vitamin E was able
to significantly boost immunity
to hepatitis B
and tetanus vaccinations
(though not to diphtheria
or pneumonia).
One randomized controlled trial
found that vitamin E
supplementation of the elderly
did not cut down on lower
respiratory tract infections
(like pneumonia)
but did reduce the incidence
of upper respiratory tract
infections
(like the common cold)
by about 20 percent
over one year.
But another study
using the same dose
found no preventive benefit,
and vitamin E supplementation
actually made the infections
they did get even worse,
with a greater number
and severity of symptoms,
including a greater likelihood
of fever
and activity restriction.
By far the largest study
on vitamin E
and respiratory infections
was the ATBC Study
that randomized
nearly 15,000 smokers
to vitamin E or placebo
for about 5 years.
No overall effect
was found either way
between the vitamin E
and placebo groups,
but upon subgroup analysis
it appeared
that while lighter smokers
living in cities
appeared to benefit
with about a 50 percent
lower risk
of catching the common cold,
vitamin E appeared
to be a detriment
to heavier smokers
living outside of cities,
resulting in about a 50 percent
increased risk.
"Accordingly,"
concluded the investigators,
"caution should be maintained
in public health
recommendations
on vitamin E supplementation
until its effects
are better understood."
The pneumonia results
from the same study
took a similar turn.
No overall effect of vitamin E
compared to placebo,
but upon further analysis,
vitamin E appeared
to decrease pneumonia risk
among lighter smokers
who exercised,
yet increased pneumonia risk
among heavier smokers
who did not.
Higher pneumonia rates
were also noted
in those randomized
to vitamin D
and were either low
or high body weight,
but only, apparently,
among those
with higher dietary
vitamin C intake.
Heavy smokers
who got a lot of C
also seemed to have
higher tuberculosis rates on E
compared to placebo.
This kind of slicing
and dicing of data
is frowned upon, as it can
spawn spurious connections,
so these findings are regarded
only as exploratory
for further
research directions.
Overall mortality
in the ATBC Study was similar
between the vitamin E
and placebo groups,
though again
there were subgroups
that appeared to have
their lives either cut short
or extended.
There have been dozens
of controlled clinical trials
on vitamin E,
and most meta-analyses
found a small
but apparent real increase
in the risk of mortality
among those randomized
to vitamin E.
In other words, those who buy
vitamin E supplements
may be, in effect, paying
to live a shorter life.
Across 46 trials,
12 percent died
in the vitamin E groups
versus about 10 percent
in the placebo groups.
This is similar to the increase
in mortality
seen with beta carotene
supplementation-
approximately 14 percent
versus 11 percent
across 26 randomized trials.
The goal of the ATBC
was to see if taking
antioxidant supplements
like vitamin E or beta carotene
could help prevent lung cancer
in smokers.
Vitamin E had no effect
on lung cancer,
and beta-carotene unexpectedly
actually increased
lung cancer rates,
but vitamin E did,
incidentally,
appear to reduce
incident prostate cancer rates.
This helped inspire
the SELECT study,
the largest cancer
prevention trial ever performed.
More than 35,000 men were
randomized to take vitamin E,
selenium, both,
or neither (just placebos).
The selenium
didn't appear to matter,
but those randomized
to the straight vitamin E group
ended up with a 17 percent
greater risk
of developing prostate cancer.
If 100 men took vitamin E
for a decade,
we would expect to see
one or two of them
to be diagnosed
with prostate cancer
that they otherwise
wouldn't have gotten
had they wasted their money
on sugar pills instead.